Here is the roadmap to
get started in it in 2025,
and it's been two years since
I've made a video on this.
Some things have changed, but first
let's talk about what hasn't changed.
This roadmap is aimed at getting you a
job in it fast and on the path to landing
your dream job.
Six figures is absolutely within reach
and you'll be surprised at how fast you
can get there. No gimmicks. No shortcuts,
just hard work on a clear path and also
no college. You don't need it. Now,
similar to our last roadmap, the
first three phases are for you.
They're for everyone.
The skills you learn here are foundational
to it no matter what path you go
down, but after that,
the world is your oyster.
What I mean is that you can
go down many different paths.
I can't cover them all here,
but I will be talking about one of the
most exciting ones, the coolest ones,
the ones you see on tv. Cybersecurity
specifically. How do you become a hacker?
Ethically, of course, and also,
please know this may be a roadmap,
but you don't necessarily have to drive
all the way down in the same order.
In fact, you may find a shortcut.
We'll talk more about that later.
And just so you know, this
roadmap is hacker approved.
John Hammond looked at it and said, yes.
This is John Hammond approved.
So here we go. Phase one.
Actually, no, no Phase zero. Yeah,
we're doing things different this year
and this might feel weird for phase zero.
I want you to start
applying for jobs right now.
I don't care that you know
nothing. That's okay. I get it.
It feels a bit cart before
horse, but lemme tell you,
you don't need IT skills to
get that first job in it.
Now I know many of these
entry-level IT help desk jobs.
It seems like they're asking
for a lot. Look at this one,
a help desk specialist in Houston, Texas.
They want you to have a year experience.
They want you to have some
strong technical skills already,
but really all they care
about is excellent customer
service skills. Trust me.
Alright, come here. Can
I tell you a secret?
I got my first IT job without a
certification to my name or really any IT
skills,
but I did have some fast
food job experience and I
was hungry not for fast food
but for IT, for learning and proving
that I could be of value to that company.
Now,
the reason I want you to apply for IT
help desk or technical support roles is
that it's the first job for most
people in it. It's entry level.
Can you skip it? It's possible. In fact,
I encourage you to apply
for jobs above that.
It's not going to hurt anything and you
never know, but if you're fresh green,
just getting started, help
desk is an amazing place to be.
You'll learn so much and you're not going
to be there for very long unless you
want to be. Help desk is
pretty fun. At that point,
it was the best job I ever had.
I actually had fun going to work
and I really didn't want to leave.
So right now, if you want
to get started in it,
polish up that resume for what you
want to do, not what you have done.
Tailor your experience to be
very IT focused. For example,
I worked at Starbucks, but you better
believe on that resume I put on there,
I fix their printer all the time. I
was the guy they would go to Chuck,
the printer's broken again. I
got you guys also on my resume.
I was very upfront about what I was
working towards, what I was studying.
We'll talk about that here in a moment
and if you want examples of what that
might look like,
I do have a video where I broke down
some really awesome resumes and reviewed
some LinkedIn profiles. Check those
out here somewhere. The holdup.
Why are we doing this?
Why are we getting a job immediately
before we learn anything? This reason,
experience is king. It's gold.
Nothing looks better on your
resume than experience. Also,
what you learn on that job will be more
valuable than anything else you study.
So phase zero,
polish up that resume and make
your LinkedIn profile look awesome.
Start applying for jobs right now,
right after this video. Seriously,
it'll take you a couple hours and
maintain a habit of regularly applying for
jobs until you get that job. And guess
what? It's okay if you don't get it.
It's okay if you go on an
interview and you fail.
You're learning so much in this process
and you're meeting people also just
going through all these different jobs
and seeing the descriptions and what
they're looking for will teach you
a lot. And also kind of a footnote,
one more thing you want to do is
start networking the social kind,
acquaint yourself with the IT world.
Start following people on Twitter and
get into Discord and start talking to
people who are like you, who are studying.
Start talking to people who
are above you, who are mentors.
The old adage is true.
It's not what it's who.
Most of the jobs I've gotten have been
through relationships that I've built.
I know phase zero is weird.
Might feel like a waste of time right now
because all you want to do is learn it
because it's awesome. Don't
skip this if you're serious.
So if you're in a place right now to
where you can get a job and start working
in it, if that's really what you want
to do, phase zero, man, say it with me.
Phase zero. Sorry,
phase one now I don't want you to move
on until you've applied for at least two
jobs. Also, leave a comment
below if you get a job. Oh,
I'd be so excited to hear that and
how encouraging will that be for other
people? Just do that. Now, phase one
compared to my last video in 2023,
it's changed a little bit,
but it's still going to be
about foundations developing
those core IT skills.
Now I'm a big believer
in IT certifications and
what they can do for your
career. You'll see many
of these on the roadmap.
The first one I recommend for
foundations is the compt A plus.
This essentially is the help
desk certification that's
going to help you land
that first job. Can you skip it? We'll
talk about that here in a second,
but here's what you're going to learn
and actually there's a new one they just
came out with launching Spring 2025
exciting. But the A plus is an IT buffet.
They're going to teach you so many things,
which is great because when
you first get started in it,
you may not know which path you want to
go down and there are a billion paths.
The a plus gives you a
chance to sample everything.
Programming may be a bit dry,
but networking is delicious and
you'll never know until you try it.
Now for most people, getting the
A plus certification is not easy.
It's a lot of information contained in
two exams each costing you $253 and yes,
that's per exam and that's
for the current exams.
I'm not sure what the 2025
exams will cost. We'll see.
Now I know for someone just starting out,
this is a lot and that
was the case for me.
I even failed one exam and had to
retake it paying more money. That hurt.
So it begs the question, is this worth
it? Do you actually need the exam?
Can't you just go study the knowledge,
learn it, save some money? Yeah, you can,
but here's the problem. How are
you going to prove that knowledge?
How are you going to prove
that to the hiring manager?
That's what the a plus is for. Compt
has done all the marketing for you.
They tell people, Hey, if someone has
this cert, they know everything. So hr,
all they have to do is go,
oh, Aaron has the a plus.
He can probably do this help desk job.
It gets you past that HR filter. So TLDR,
you need the knowledge
certification. It's optional,
but it'll help you get that foot in
the door and land that first job.
Now how do you get the A plus?
Where do you learn this stuff from?
There are free and paid options for
free. You can't beat Professor Messer.
He has an entire A plus course on
YouTube. You can watch it right now.
Now for a paid option, there's IT
Pro tv, which I love. Link below.
Actually now it's called IT Pro and also
this will be a shameless plug for me.
I'm building something which
means it's not done yet,
but it's going to be kind of different.
You'll see. Just keep in mind,
it is still in the building phase and
part of this new thing, my academy,
there'll be an entire
CompTIA a plus course,
a training series that I'm pouring
my blood, sweat, and coffee into.
It's something that I wish would've
been around when I first started my IT
career and started learning.
So if you like to start studying this
as we're building it, check it out.
Link below.
It's currently 12 bucks a month and
every penny is going towards making this
thing awesome. And yes, I will be
covering the 2025 compt a plus exams.
Now the goal with phase one is to get
your a plus or at least equivalent
knowledge, but we're not quite done yet.
This is where my roadmap's going to start
being a little weird compared to 2023,
and by weird I mean awesome.
Now this is optional because I
don't want you to be overwhelmed,
but while you're studying for your A plus,
I want you to start learning
Linux and not just Linux.
I want you to start
learning coding as well,
specifically either Python
or go Python's the favorite.
So I go with that Python, I don't
want to be confusing. Now again,
getting the A plus is
still your main focus,
but I want you to start becoming
familiar with Linux and Python.
Now what does that look like? How are
you going to do that? Start simple.
Maybe one day a week.
Saturdays you'll spend 30 minutes
learning Linux and 30 minutes learning
Python or an hour each, two hours each.
I don't really care what you
do as long as you do something.
Now where do you learn?
What are the resources?
There are a bajillion out there for Linux.
I have a free Linux for Hackers course.
You could watch one episode a week for
Python. I have a Python for everyone.
Course these are both free on YouTube
by the way. Now why Linux and coding?
Well, you're going to see this
everywhere at every step of your journey,
start learning it now again,
even if it's just a little bit.
Now we're not done with phase
one yet. You thought we were.
We're not also in phase one. I want you
to start building out your home lab.
This is where you get a chance to put
into practice everything you're learning.
Don't just learn the theory, take
notes and memorize things. No,
do the things. For example,
when you're learning about virtual
machines in the a plus in your home lab,
install virtual box and
set up a virtual machine.
Install Ubuntu as part
of your Linux practice.
When you're learning about networks,
install a router in your house.
Replace your home router with
PF sense. Install a DNS server.
Most if not all of these things can be
done for free and it's going to be this.
Check this out.
I call these projects resume building
moments because you know what else you're
going to be doing in phase one.
You're going to be applying for
jobs if you don't already have one.
Keep applying. Keep refining your resume.
When you deploy a DNS
server into your home,
put on your resume a project that you
deployed a DNS server into your house.
That's cool. That's real tech,
that's real it lemme tell you,
if you have a home lab, you look good.
That communicates passion and drive.
Man.
When I saw resumes or people were putting
their own projects in their house on
their resume,
I love hiring those types of people
that they are passionate about this.
Even when they go home,
I know they're going to be thinking about
this stuff and learning and growing.
That's what employers want and
that's surprisingly hard to hire for.
So if you can demonstrate that,
oh my gosh. Now I know phase one,
that's a luck, right? Feel
free to cut some things out.
If all you can manage is the a
plus during this time, that's fine.
You can do these in order. Finish your
A plus the Newsome, Lins and Python,
implement some home lab ideas.
It's up to you where you can
do it all within one week.
Now to fully graduate from phase one,
I'm estimating it'll take you
roughly two to three months.
Of course this will vary based
on your life, your schedule,
how much time you have, but if
you work hard, you can do it,
but two to three months if you maintain
a pretty consistent study schedule
should be good. Now on to phase two. Yes,
we're finally moving on to phase two.
I know phase two is all about dipping
your toes in the security water.
It's kind of a cool brand name dibs.
The focal point of this phase is gaining
the security plus from CompTIA. Yes,
another IT certification,
but this thing looks really,
really good on your resume,
similar to the A plus,
the security plus will teach
you a ton of information,
but here it's security focused.
They might be thinking, Chuck,
I'm not going into hacking. I
don't want to be a security expert.
Why do I have to learn this? Listen,
security will be part of every IT role
you have. The more you know about it,
the better. And for phase two, we're
not going super deep into security,
but we're giving you enough knowledge
and enough credentials to find in land an
amazing job. Now, why security
plus why another certification?
This looker is going to do two things
for you. Knowledge, there's a ton of it.
This is a security buffet
and similar to the a plus,
you're going to find out
about roles and paths,
but just cybersecurity that you
didn't know existed. It's a big world.
Number two, this is definitely a
checkbox cert. What does that mean?
A lot of companies want
you to have this. In fact,
this is one of the most popular certs
for people who want to work for the
government in any capacity because
it satisfies the DOD 85 70 directive,
which lays out the minimum requirements
for IT and cybersecurity roles.
The security plus is the
easiest way to check that box.
You'll find that most roles just
want you to have it by default.
Currently the security plus will cost
you $404 and that's just one exam.
And again, yes,
you can learn the knowledge within
the security plus without getting the
certification, but the certification
looks really good on your resume.
Now where can you study for the security?
Plus again, free and paid options,
free Professor master coming in,
he has an entire security plus course
for free on YouTube for a paid option.
I do recommend it Pro and know
they're not sponsoring this video.
I just really do like
them. And full disclosure,
the link below will be an affiliate link,
meaning that when you sign
up you don't pay anymore,
but I do get a small kickback
for telling you about 'em.
Now while the focal point
of phase two is security,
plus there's going to be more
Linux. Linux becomes very,
very important in this phase. And
because we're in the security phase,
let's have you do some Linux
that's security focused.
There's a free site called Over the wire.
This place is amazing and they
have a path called Bandit,
which when you go through it will teach
you a ton of Linux basics. It's amazing,
very, very fun. Check it
out. Also in this phase,
no surprise is more coding Python at
this phase, keep learning the basics,
but then I want you to challenge
yourself to build some kind of thing,
a project. Think something that
you could add to your resume.
Another resume building moment. One idea
is to build a simple network scanner,
scan your network and look for
open ports using Python. And again,
similar to phase one, don't stress about
the Python and Linux side of things.
Focus on security plus get that
on your resume. But if can,
if it doesn't overwhelm you, one to
two hours a week more. If you're crazy,
the more Linux and Python you learn,
the better It's going
to be awesome for you.
And at this point I'm going to
start sounding like a broken record.
Do some home lab stuff,
what you're learning in the security plus
what you're learning through Linux and
Python. Do some things in your home lab.
Automate some things
with Linux and Python.
Get on YouTube and look for fun projects.
I do all kinds of stuff in the home lab.
Just do something and add it
to your resume. And finally,
keep applying for stinking jobs
if you don't already have one.
And always keep that resume up to date.
This space should roughly take you two
to three months and I know what you're
probably thinking. I would be
thinking the same thing. Chuck,
you're being very vague about how
much Linux and Python to learn.
How much do I do in my home
lab? I'm doing that on purpose.
I don't want to overwhelm you also,
that would make this video way too long.
But if you'd like me to make a more
detailed roadmap where I'm like at this
point do this project, at this point
you should know this much Python.
If you'd like to see that, let me know.
That may be a video I make in the future.
So phase two, two to three months,
which of course will be determined
by how much time you have and other
variables.
It's time for a coffee break and this
coffee break in this video is sponsored by
Bamboo Labs,
which I'm actually really excited to
talk about because I've been using Bamboo
Labs forever. They're one of the
first 3D printers I ever bought.
And the reason I'm excited is because
they're going to help you with your resume
building moments, the chance for you
to shine and show off your home labs.
I got into 3D printing about maybe two,
three years ago and I bought
this 3D printer. I hated it.
Took me forever to set up, almost pulled
out my beard, thank goodness I didn't.
And the printing was slow, so I'm like
there's got to be something better.
And that's when I found Bamboo
Labs. I bought this one.
I don't think I worked for two weeks. I
would just stand there and watch things.
Print Bamboo Labs is one of those ones
that it's advanced enough to make you
excited about diving deeper, but it's
simple enough for anyone to approach it.
Like someone in my church, he just
bought a 3D printer for his kids.
They set it up and just started
printing everything. In fact,
they bought this one here.
The Bamboo Labs a one combo.
This thing is ridiculous,
super fast, easy to set up.
My team can set it up and they're
not the most technical people.
They're working on it. And the deal on
this thing at the time of this video,
it's $489 for the printer
and then this a MS light.
What that means is that you
can do multicolor prints,
you can design your model,
slice it with a bunch of colors and
it'll just change it out for you.
Now back to home lab stuff. You can
make your home lab that much more great.
Make your resume building
moments a bit prettier,
a bit more functional with a 3D printer.
So when I did my travel mass video,
I needed something that
would house all my stuff,
my SSDs and everything
printed that sucker.
And then me and my team 3D printed a
few more things just to give you some
ideas. This raspberry pie case,
sure you can buy a case online,
but making your own, printing
your own, that's way cooler.
It's SSD Mount for maybe whatever
server you're going to be building,
not as flashy but functional.
This SD card holder,
I've actually printed a
few of these in the past.
We legit use these every day and as
you're building out your home lab,
you'll probably end up having a rack.
So you'll want to rack mount
your raspberry pie, print
that and check this out.
They have this thing called Maker World.
It's a world full of things you can print
and what makes it special is that when
you select one of these,
you don't have to change any of the
settings or alter it for your specific
printer, which you used to have to do. No,
you just select your printer and
the settings are already there.
So thanks again to Bamboo Labs
for sponsoring this video.
If you want this A one combo,
check out my link below and
now back to the roadmap.
Now before we move on to phase three,
just know that in phase one and phase
two should also be continuing with
networking, social networking, keep
talking to people, keep rubbing shoulders.
Again,
you never know who is going to be
responsible for getting you that next job,
make friends, make contacts.
Now speaking of networking,
let's talk about phase three. It's
all networking. My favorite part,
networking is the bread and butter of it.
You have to know it and
when you get into it,
you'll find out that you love to
know it. Networking is the best part.
I know it's completely subjective and
I'm completely biased. Network, Chuck.
I mean you saw it coming, right?
But you don't want to skip this.
It's like eating your vegetables,
except these vegetables are delicious.
Now with networking similar
to our other phases,
we're going to focus on
a certification here.
We actually have a couple of options.
Now, if you saw my last video,
there won't be a big surprise here.
My favorite networking
certification is the Cisco CNA.
This sucker right here is probably one
of the best certifications you can get
and put on your resume period. This
chumps 'em all at this level. Anyway,
employers love this one.
It's the gold standard,
but there is another option I want to
shout out. And that's the CompTIA Network.
Plus it's another very, very popular
networking certification. Now,
why would you choose one over the
other? Well, Cisco, it's harder.
It's going to take you more
time, take you more study,
it might kick your butt a bit more.
But the CNA is more valuable probably
because it's harder and demonstrates
practical skills.
And one of the reasons it's so practical
is because it's Cisco focused with the
certification, you're going to
learn networking inside and out,
but you're also going to be learning
how to use Cisco products, their CLI.
You'll be learning about their automation
products, their security products.
So this is the no-brainer if you're
going to go down the network engineering
path or network admin path. But
if you're going somewhere else,
CNA might be a bit too much for you.
That's where the Network plus comes in.
It's vendor neutral so you're not focusing
on any one vendor and you'll still
pick up networking knowledge, learning
what a router is, a switch subnetting,
they'll both look great on your resume.
CCNA will make you look better. Also,
it will only help you to know how
to use Cisco stuff because Cisco is
everywhere. A ton of companies use them.
They have been dominant for a long
time. Let's talk about pricing.
The Network plus will cost you $369.
It is one exam and the
CCNA will cost you $300.
So it actually is the better deal
even though it's harder. Now,
where do you go to learn? Where can
you learn this stuff for Network Plus,
similar to the other
CompTIA certifications,
professor Messer co and Clutch has a
free network plus course on YouTube for
paid IT Pro has a pretty good network
plus course. And then for the CC NA,
I'm actually really excited
to tell you about this.
There is a and paid option free.
There's a channel called Jeremy's,
IT Labs on YouTube and he has
an entire course CCNA for free,
which is kind of insane because the
CC NA is very, very hard to teach.
It's a lot of content. And Jeremy's a
friend of mine, he's an awesome dude.
He also lives in Japan, which is
very cool. After the paid option,
this is what I'm excited
about. I mentioned my academy
earlier, my new thing,
I'm building the thing that's
going to be different. Well,
I'm not building it alone and I don't
think I've publicly announced this to
anyone yet. So you're first to hear,
I've partnered with a guy
who taught me networking.
That's where I learned everything.
I know he's the guy who got me so excited
about it and really he's responsible
for what I'm doing today. His name
is Jeremy Charra. He's A-C-C-I-E.
Incredible teacher.
He's where I learned how to teach and
he has created the most amazing CCNA
course, the best one he's ever made on
our academy. So similar to the A plus,
it is currently on the academy.
We're still in our building phase,
but you can go there right now and
become part of this as we're building it.
But please keep in mind disclaimer,
it's not completely ready yet.
We're building it,
but I would love for you to come check
it out and become part of what we're
doing. It is going to be something
different. That's all I can tell you now.
So pick your poison CC A or Network Plus,
and then you probably saw this
coming more Python and more Linux.
And in the networking phase,
try to make your Linux and Python
study be networking focused.
A big part of the Cisco CC
NA is network automation,
which largely involves
doing things with Python,
logging into routers and switches
and automating things they can do.
It's very fun. Set aside two to three
hours a week and just spend time with it.
Continue to get familiar with the Linux
terminal programming and Python and just
let those skills compliment the main
focus, which here is networking. Again,
doing this is going to make you super
human. You're going to be amazing.
I mean you already are, but this
will make you that much better.
And of course in this phase
we'll be doing more home.
But here I want to give you a
challenge. We mentioned in phase one,
replacing your router with PF
sense as an option. And this phase,
I want to challenge you to actually
do this. This is your homework.
Replace your home network
with another network.
This could be buying old
Cisco stuff off eBay.
This could be putting a PF sense
router in installing Unify.
And then I want you to do things
like monitor your network,
monitor your internet quality,
be really nerdy about it,
and then all that stuff you're doing,
slap that onto a resume and keep
applying for jobs. And then of course,
keep networking. Keep talking
to people. Keep hanging out.
Now how long this phase will take you
depends on your certification choice.
Did you choose CCNA?
Did you choose Network plus CCNA will
obviously take longer because it is
harder. I would estimate two to
four months to complete phase three,
leaning more on the four month
range. If we're talking about CNA,
this is a very aggressive timeline,
being very consistent with your study,
don't feel bad if you have to extend
this out. Just put a date in there,
be consistent. Show up every day. Now if
you get to phase three and you're done,
you're amazing.
You've laid the most incredible
IT foundation and from
here you can go anywhere,
pick any path. I believe you'll
succeed. You'll be a rock star.
But before you go anywhere else, before
you jump into a new learning path,
we've got just a little bitty phase to
make sure you're where you need to be.
And that's phase 3.5. What? Yeah,
no track. Track with me here.
We're going to come down
here and go to phase 3.5.
It looks so weird. 3.5 this
phase is called get that job.
If you don't have a job by this point,
then I want your full-time study to be
get a job because if you've gone through
phase one, two, and three,
you've got more than enough to land
a job and don't beat yourself down.
If you haven't gotten a job yet, that's
fine. I just wouldn't go any further.
I would pour all of your efforts
into doing this. So keep learning,
keep building up your skillset.
Keep sharpening the skills you've
learned and keep adding to your home lab.
Keep doing labs and projects.
Keep adding to your resume.
Keep applying for jobs, keep going to
interviews, practice, keep networking.
The whole point of all of this
is to get you a job and frankly,
when you're at the point of phase
3.5, you can apply for many,
many types of jobs. The
CNA, you look really good.
And if you've got the security plus and
a plus and you've got Python and Linux
and you've been adding to your resume
with projects, you look really good,
entry-level beginner
and intermediate jobs,
you can apply for those and you're
competitive. Now after phase 3.5,
pick your path. There are a billion.
Hopefully by this time you've kind of
figured out what you like or what you want
to be. You may have fallen
in love with security.
Maybe networking was your
calling system. Administration.
You learn some things about cloud
and cloud sounds awesome. Go do that.
These are all different paths that'll
have different requirements and alas,
I cannot cover them all. Did I just
say alas? I did. I'm going with it.
But if you do want me to cover others,
let me know in the comments below.
Right now I'm going to cover one path
that is special to me because I'm going
down it right now. And
that's the hacking path,
specifically offensive security
or otherwise known as red teaming.
Ethical hacking pen
testing. It has many names.
It's the flashy stuff you always
hear about. It is very cool.
It's not the only path in
cybersecurity, it's just one of many,
but it's the most popular.
You hear about learning.
Hacking is a whole journey in and
of itself. But to get started,
which is I'm going to be able to
show you, it would take forever.
I would target a cert, no surprise here.
And actually three different certs.
I would start out with
a junior level cert.
A couple I love are the EJPT or
the pen test Plus, they're easier,
more approachable,
and it'll dip your toe into what
it means to be an ethical hacker,
which is a different mindset.
Like yes, to be a hacker,
you have to know phase
one, two, and three.
All the skills you learn in those
phases will be used the opposite way.
Normally you're learning how to
build it, protect it, defend it.
Now you're having to reverse that
thinking and go, Hey, how can I break it?
The EJPT will be $249 including training
for three months through INE because
they run and operate the EJPT. And
I believe you get two attempts,
which is kind of awesome.
And if I had to choose between
the PEN Test Plus and EJPT,
I'd probably choose the EJPT.
The PEN test plus will be $381,
not including training, but
it is a bit more well known.
So if you're looking to put something
on your resume, that will look good.
Now I'm going to say this.
There's only one hacking, sir,
I'm going to list here that will
actually look good on your resume.
That will actually make people go, oh,
they know what they're talking about.
Or at least they're starting to.
The next one I would get the next phase
of your journey would be the CPTS or the
Certified Penetration Testing
Specialist from Hack the Box.
This is the one I'm working on right now.
The CPTS is interesting because you
do have to go through the Hack the Box
Academy modules to complete it. That's
what they tell you. I feel like.
What is Hack the Box? Oh, if
you want to become a hacker,
this is the place you want to be.
Before they have their academy
and their own certification,
they were the place to
go to practice hacking.
They would create boxes that you can
literally hack. It's very gamified,
very fun.
So when they created their own academy
and then a certification to go along with
it, oh, I'm down. I've been
a fan for a very long time.
I was trying to find the
pricing therapist. $490.
I don't think that includes
training. Lemme just find out.
I think that's just for the
voucher. Now the CPTS is fairly new,
so it's not quite resume
gold, not like the next one,
which is probably the best hacking
certification you can put on your resume,
and that's the OSCP. Now, the
OSCP is on my list to get,
but I'm going with the CPTS first because
it's a bit easier and I want to ease
my way up to it. But for a long time,
the OSEP has been the gold standard.
They do have their own official
training course called the Pen 200,
and they have an exam bundle
that'll cost you roughly 1600 bucks.
But that includes the course 90 days
of lab access in one exam attempt,
which is extremely practical
along with the CPTS and EJBT.
But I think the OSEP is probably the most
practical, if not the most difficult.
Now at this phase,
you're going to be using lots of
Linux and potentially lots of Python.
As you're going through
these hacking certifications,
you'll probably need a lot of
these to be able to take the exam.
What's interesting though is the OSCP
has recently allowed you to use Chad GPT
during the exam recognizing
the fact that hey,
modern engineers and modern hackers
are going to have AI right there.
Now this is just the very
beginning of a red teaming journey.
Will this be enough to get you a
job as a pin tester? I think so.
Similar to the other phases, start
applying immediately for what you want.
Don't wait to get your
first hacking certification.
Just start applying and while
you're applying, keep studying.
Now one note about this particular
phase, the hacking phase.
If you're confident you
want to go down that,
then I would also try to sprinkle in some
more hacking CTFs or capture the flag
events throughout your learning journey.
There's an amazing free CTF
software out there called PICO ctf.
Very beginner friendly and you can
interject that at any phase doing CTFs and
labs that are pertinent to the phase
you're at so you don't get overwhelmed.
It could be part of your Linux learning,
your Python learning and will give
you a feel for what A CTF feels like,
which if you're in the hacking realm,
CTFs are how people practice
their hacking skills.
It's a gamified attempt to hack something
to capture a flag that's hidden behind
security measures. But
there is a vulnerability you
have to exploit. Exploit.
It's kind of funny.
It's one of those words where you have
to put emphasis on whether or not it's
going to be a verb or a noun.
It's weird. So here we are,
the map phases one through
three, that's for everyone.
Everyone in it will benefit from going
through these phases and at every step be
applying for a job, never wait
to start earning experience.
But now we're at the section where we're
going to talk about shortcuts because
not everyone's going to follow this
roadmap sequentially, linearly.
I mean initially you'll want to follow
it just so because as a beginner you
probably don't know much, but you may
not be a beginner. So this roadmap,
tailor it to you,
make sure you have a good handle
on the basics and the foundations.
But there are points where you
could skip a phase. Like phase one,
you might already know all this stuff.
You've been playing with Linux and
Python, you know how to build a pc.
You've already got a home lab.
Just start applying for jobs
and move on to another phase.
Maybe you feel like you
already know enough security,
you don't need a certification, just
skip ahead, jump into networking.
Just keep in mind these certifications
are there to make your resume look
better. You don't need
it to gain the knowledge,
but you do need it to prove
the knowledge in most cases.
But it's up to you whether or not you
want to skip any phase. Just know that.
Let's say you skip phases one and two and
you just go straight to CC NA when you
get your CCC NA. No one cares if you
have your A plus or your network.
Plus all they see is the CCC NA and they
assume that everything else or at least
have passing knowledge. Also, keep
in mind that when you get a job,
which again is the goal of every
single step when you get a job that may
change this roadmap for you. For example,
you may apply for a job that
you think you'll never get,
like a SOC analyst job or a job in a
knock and you're able to skip the help
desk. And when you land that job,
they may want you to learn something.
They may want you to jump
straight to the CNA cyber ops,
which is a certification we didn't talk
about because it is more specialist to
blue Team Cybersecurity.
But my point is that just change
adapt to your circumstances and the
opportunities that are presented to you.
Don't feel like you have
to follow this just so,
and when you get a chance to
take a shortcut, take it now,
I don't mean a shortcut to knowledge,
always spend the time to learn something,
but if you can jump into a job you're
not ready for and they just hired you,
do that, that's awesome.
You can learn on the job.
That's what most people do anyway.
Now, what about college, university?
I didn't mention any of this here. Are
degrees worth it? Yes, they can be.
I didn't feature that on my
roadmap because I'm a big
fan of doing it this way.
I don't have a degree. I didn't need
one. But you might need one or want one,
and that's totally fine. It will
be valuable and it will open doors.
It might be a very time consuming and
expensive door, but it'll get you there.
But keep this in mind. If
you're going for an IT degree,
many of these degrees when you finish,
you're still going to need what's
covered in these certifications.
They don't often include that in
your curriculum. When you come out,
you're going to be like, oh, I still
need to get my CCNA and my security plus.
No one's going to hire me
without those. That's happens.
That happens all the time. So my
advice, if you want that degree,
find a degree program that includes
certifications as part of your curriculum.
So for example, one I love is WGU or
the Western Governor's University.
Part of many of their IT
degrees is C-C-N-A-A plus AWS
certifications for cloud.
It's like part of their final exam
for the networking section of classes.
You have to pass your
certification. That's amazing.
You get a degree and you
get certifications, you
come out a rockstar. Yes,
it will be more expensive
than just doing this yourself,
but if you want a degree,
that's what I recommend.
Alright, so network.
Chuck sent me his roadmap,
a little 2025 plan to get a job in it.
Maybe a little bit of cybersecurity.
So I did want to take a quick look
starting off. He's saying, look,
you should be studying Linux and Python
early in the journey and then keep doing
it all the way throughout.
Not going to lie,
I completely a thousand
percent agree with this.
Maybe it doesn't need
to be strictly Python,
but absolutely I feel like using the
Linux command line and at least scripting
in a language like Python or
writing code or programming,
automating in one way or another,
that is something that
should really be solidified.
And so definitely worth starting as
early as you can and still doing it all
throughout. Those are skills that give
you superpowers, not going to lie.
And then Chuck goes into a lot about
networking net plus versus CCC NA or
if it is needed at all. So look, again,
I have to speak from just
me and my experience.
I don't know what CCC NA
GOs darn is, truth be told.
Maybe I'm out of the loop. I could
very well just not be educated there,
but I have not particularly
needed a ton of in-depth,
very granular networking
insight and experience.
I think from the hacking or
cybersecurity sense, if you know, hey,
what the heck IP addresses are, what
a general cider, class C, class B,
whatever network and subnets
are, that's kind of enough.
You don't need to be building out any
VLANs or crafting and architecting a
whole blown network. Next
is on the hacking path.
Some of the certifications with EJPT,
PENTEST plus maybe CPTS and OSCP.
This is just John speaking. I
don't know about EJPT these days.
I don't know if it's alive and well,
but I might very well
just be out of the loop.
And I have not personally
taken PENTEST Plus,
so I don't feel like I have any authority
to kind of speak on that as much.
I do think either of them
are a good choice though.
Pentest plus especially might give you
a little bit more runway because any of
the plus CompTIA certifications
are just generally well-known.
But I would consider OSCP still
the crown jewel I'd suggest look,
if that's what you want to go for it,
if you want some intermediary steps,
CPTS or any others that you're interested
in can still be stepping stones.
But make sure you've got,
this is your target in mind and don't
hesitate drive towards that. Ooh,
the last one is spicy. His
view on college, look, college,
undergrad, school, university,
whatever. I kind of agree with Chuck.
Not going to lie, I think it is optional.
It is not needed in the absolute
strict sense of the words,
but it can be extremely helpful
to go through. It's subjective.
It's super subjective to you and your
case for anyone tuning in. You can crawl,
walk,
and run just fine without a college degree
or anything to kind of get your foot
in the door for job hunting.
You can find places,
occupations and people that will employ
you without a college degree if you
prove your merit and competency. But
it is an extra notch on your belt.
So there's nothing really wrong with
that. As I mentioned, crawl, walk, run.
Hey, you can get a little bit of a
speed boost if you go for college.
Maybe that helps get things up and
running at the start, but it's optional.
College can be good, but I don't
think you need it a thousand percent.
So lemme end cap this. It's
been a very long video,
but times have changed and times
are changing rapidly right now.
What's going to happen with ai? Where
are our jobs going to go? I don't know.
No one knows. We can all guess.
But what we do know is that
you need skills. The skills
covered in this roadmap,
foundational skills,
and people still hire for those skills
and I think they'll be in demand for a
long time. And if they aren't,
hey, you'll learn something anyway.
And I know this roadmap ended up
being very specific to hacking.
What other roadmaps do you want to
see? Cloud engineer, network engineer,
more blue team, comment
below. That's all I got.
This is the first video of
2025. I hope you're doing well.
I'll catch you guys next time.